GUILLERMO MARTIN

Alameda, CA 94501

Phone: (757) 620-2701 | Email: gscalica@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/guillermo-martin-10441046/J Github: https://github.com/Guillermo-MartinJ

Portfolio: https://guillermo-martin.github.io/gcm-portfolio/

SUMMARY

Full Stack Web Developer with a passion for the front end and building functional and aesthetically pleasing Web applications that impact user experience (UX). Background in biology and forensic science, graduate of the Berkeley Coding Boot Camp Full Stack Web Development program. Enjoy cross collaboration with teams and developers to design and implement applications. Proficient in browser-based technologies, API Interaction, Deployment/Command-Line Fundamentals, Databases, Server Side Development, and Quality Assurance and have foundational knowledge in computer science applied to JavaScript.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Web Technologies: HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript (ES6), jQuery, Bootstrap, and React

Server-side Technologies: Node.js and Express.js Databases: MySQL, MongoDB, and Mongoose API Interaction: API, REST API, JSON, and AJAX Deployment: Git, GitHub Pages, and Heroku

Other: Command Line, MVC, Computer Science applied to JavaScript, Quality Assurance, Redux, User

Authentication, Content Management Systems (Squarespace, WordPress)

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

Freelance Web Developer

Positive Planet - November 2020 - Present

June 2020 – Present

A non-profit organization that supports and provides the underprivileged with the means to become entrepreneurs.

• Responsibilities: collaborating with other web developers to use WordPress, HTML5, and CSS3 to style the "Accelerator Hub" landing page and make its design responsive according to mockups and specifications provided by a graphic designer.

Oakland Peace Center - <u>https://www.oaklandpeacecenter.org/</u> **-** June 2020 - September 2020 A small non-profit website previously built using the Content Management System, Squarespace.

Responsibilities: redesigning the website using Squarespace, HTML5, and CSS3 in order to streamline
the user experience (UX) and create a more appealing and engaging user interface (UI), collaborating
with Board Members in order to maintain company brand and improve brand awareness, providing
training on the use of Squarespace to the Donor Engagement Manager.

PROJECTS

Drunk on Games | https://github.com/jngo2013/gameWebsite | In Progress - October 2020 - Present A full stack Web application designed to promote a client's board game hobby by providing information and alternative rules on board games.

- Collaborating with a full stack web developer to build both the front end and back end using an MVC framework.
- Responsibilities: creating and styling React user interface (UI) components, setting up the Express server, creating RESTful API routes and functions to query a database, and troubleshooting the front end and back end.

• Technologies, Tools, and Frameworks: MongoDB, Mongoose, Express.js, React, Node.js, React Bootstrap, Axios, React Router DOM, HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript (ES6), Figma, and GitHub.

Blog Site | https://github.com/Kerry-Jr/Project02 | https://project02blog.herokuapp.com/

A full stack Web application that allows anyone to post their thoughts, search for recipes, or search for information regarding Pokemon.

- Collaborated with four other developers.
- Responsibilities: working on the front end and assisting with architecture and functionality, creating and styling the React user interface (UI) components, acquainting teammates with the GitHub workflow, and assisting other teammates with troubleshooting the front end and back end.
- Technologies, Tools, and Frameworks: HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript (ES6), Bootstrap, Express.js, React, Node.js, Heroku, Travis CI, Moment.js, mySQL2, React-Spring, Axios, React Bootstrap, React Router DOM, dotenv, Pokemon API, and recipe finder API.

Planet | https://github.com/jngo2013/Project03 | https://blooming-atoll-78659.herokuapp.com/

A full stack Web application that allows users to create, join, edit, delete, and track their events.

- Collaborated with three other developers.
- Responsibilities: working on the front end and assisting with architecture and functionality, creating and styling React user interface (UI) components, assisting with user experience (UX), assisting other teammates with troubleshooting the front end and back end.
- Technologies, Tools, and Frameworks: HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript (ES6), MongoDB, Express.js, React, Node.js, Semantic UI React, Redux, Travis CI, Heroku, Mongoose, User Authentication technologies, React Router DOM, and Axios.

ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

Criminalist III (Forensic Scientist) Alameda County Sheriff's Office

May 2009 – July 2019 Oakland, CA

Responsibilities: conducting independent laboratory examination and analysis on hundreds of cases in Forensic Biology and DNA, documenting findings in laboratory reports, processing crime scenes and conducting vehicle examinations, conducting technical and administrative reviews, testifying as an expert witness, and managing the exchange of criminally-sensitive information with local, state, and national law enforcement agencies.

EDUCATION

Certificate in Full Stack Web Development: University of California, Berkeley Extension, Berkeley, CA A rigorous and fast-paced, 12-week full-time, Full Stack Web Development course that covers the theory and application of Web development to provide the knowledge and skills to build full stack Web applications and to become a full stack Web developer. The following topics were covered in this program: Browser Based Technologies, API Interaction, Server Side Development, Databases, Quality Assurance, Deployment/Command-Line Fundamentals, and Computer Science applied to JavaScript.

Master of Science, Forensic Science: University of Central Oklahoma, Edmond, OK

Non-degree coursework in Cellular and Molecular Biology: Old Dominion University, Norfolk, VA

Bachelor of Science, Biology: James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA